Ziyu Li

@ zli17nl@gmail.com

+31 630983914

y ziyuli_li

ziyuli.me

zLizy



Personal Statement

Committed and dedicated, my passion lies in exploring the fusion of database and machine learning (DBML) realms. With a solid background in research and practical experience, I am deeply engaged in advancing impactful research endeavors. My current focus revolves around (meta)data management and representation, aiming to optimize machine learning workflows for heightened efficiency and effectiveness.

Experience

2024.2 - Now	Postdoc researcher	TU Delft	Delft, Netherlands		
	➤ Web Information Systems (WIS) group				
2019 - 2024	PhD researcher	TU Delft	Delft, Netherlands		
	> Web Information Systems (WIS) group				
2018.5 - 2018.8	Data analyst intern	Corbion	Amsterdam, Netherlands		
2016.7 - 2016.9	Android developer intern		South China University of Technology		
	> Communication & Computer Network Lab of Guangdong				

Education

2019 - 2024	PhD (Computer Science)	TU Delft	Delft, Netherlands		
	Research direction: Databases, Machine Learning				
	Supervisors: Prof. Alessandro Bozzon, Dr. Asterios Katsifodimos				
	Dissertation: On the Utility of Metadata to Optimize ML Workflows				
2017 - 2019	Master (Data Intrinsic Track)	TU Delft	Delft, Netherlands		
	Thesis topic: Graph, Network embe	edding			
	Thesis: Diffusion Based Temporal Network Embedding for Link Prediction				
2013 - 2017	Bachelor (Network Engineering)	South China Uni	iversity of Technology		
	Guangzhou, China				
	'				



➤ TransferGraph: a novel framework that reformulates model selection as a graph learning problem. TransferGraph constructs a graph using extensive metadata extracted from models and datasets, while capturing their inherent relationships. We accumulated more than 100 real datasets, both images and texts, and over 300 open-source models for CV and NLP tasks.

Library: pytorch-geometric, transformers

- > Macaroni: a tool designed and implemented to demonstrate the metamodel that represents the metadata of models and datasets in structured and queryable manner. Macaroni supports metadata search as well as automatic model evaluation, in total more than 800 model-dataset pairs are evaluated. Toolkits: MongoDB, transformers
- **>** ML inference query optimization: we exploit metadata to optimize for ML inference queries, where predicates in the queries are ML models. User may impose constraints on multiple aspects, such as execution cost and accuracy performance. We formulate the problem as a Mixed Integer Programming (MIP) and the subsequent development of a MIP-based optimizer.

i Competences & Languages

Data Analysis R, Pandas, Numpy, Matplotlib, ggplot2, Keras, Scikit-learn

Graph pytorch-geometric, NetworkX **Optimization** Gurobi

Tools SSH, Git, Docker Programming Python, R

Framework/Library PyTorch, TensorFlow, transformers

ML/DL Computer Vision, Natural Language Processing, RAG

Language English (fluent); Chinese (mother language); Dutch (A2)



Selected Publications

Conference

- > Ziyu Li, Alessandro Bozzon, Rihan Hai, and et al. "Model Selection with Model Zoo via Graph Learning" In 2024 IEEE 40th International Conference on Data Engineering (ICDE), IEEE, 2024.
- > Ziyu Li, Mariette Schönfeld, Asterios Katsifodimos, and et al. "Optimizing ML Inference Queries Under Constraints." In International Conference on Web Engineering, pp. 51-66. Cham: Springer Nature Switzerland, 2023.
- > Ziyu Li, Mariette Schönfeld, and Asterios Katsifodimos. "Optimizing machine learning inference queries for multiple objectives." In 2023 IEEE 39th International Conference on Data Engineering Workshops (ICDEW), pp. 74-78. IEEE, 2023.

Journal

- > Ziyu Li, Wenbo Sun, Rihan Hai, and et al. "Amalur: the convergence between data integration and machine learning." IEEE Transactions on Knowledge and Data Engineering (2024).
- > Ziyu Li, Marco Brambilla, and Alessandro Bozzon, et al. "Metadata Representations for Queryable Repositories of Machine Learning Models." IEEE Access (2023).
- > Xiuxiu Zhan, Ziyu Li, Masuda N., et al. "Susceptible-infected-spreading-based network embedding in static and temporal networks"[J]. EPJ Data Science, 2020, 9(1): 30.

Activities

2023.9 - 2024.5	Co-chair with Prof. Dr. Carsten Binnig and Dr. Gerardo Vitagliano		
	at 3rd DBML workshop at International Conference on Data Engineering (ICDE)		
2023.5	Invited as reviewer for IEEE Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems		
2020 - 2024	Coached in total seven master students		